Guide to the John Howard Papers, 1950-2013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
John Howard papers 1950-2013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Howard, John.
9 Linear Feet 6750 Items
John Howard, born June 12, 1962, is a Professor of American Studies at King's College London.
The collection represents the papers of John Howard, including personal papers, professional papers, oral histories, and audiovisual materials. It includes materials on his research and writings on Southern American gender and sexuality studies, particularly gay men.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Howard Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2013.
Biographical Note
John Howard, born June 12, 1962, is a Professor of American Studies at King's College London. He completed his undergraduate work at University of Virginia, receiving his MBA from University of Mississippi and his MA in American Studies at University of Alabama. Howard was the first externally hired full-time director of the Duke LGBT student center.
His work focuses on queer history, documentary photography, Japanese-American and African-American histories, nuclear proliferation and protest, and the American South. Howard was the co-author and signatory of the Historians' Amicus Brief, Supreme Court, Lawrence v. Texas, in 2003. He has received awards and commendations from Fulbright Commission, Rockefeller Foundation, Arts and Humanities Research Council, Delfina Studio Trust amongst others. Howard is involved with a number of activist organizations, including Queer Nation and the campaign to Free Chelsea Manning.
Collection Overview
The John Howard Papers collection is comprised of five series: Personal Papers, Professional Papers, Writings, Oral Histories and Audiovisual Materials. The materials detail Howard's professional life, with undergraduate and graduate work, activism and his professional career forming the core of the collection.
The Personal Papers Series consists of items from his early life, including diplomas and test scores, undergraduate paper topics and a playlist for his band. It also includes the UK immigration case paperwork for Howard's former partner, Novid Parsi.
The Professional Papers Series is divided into eight subseries: professional files, activist organizations, conferences, research, clippings, correspondence, teaching, and miscellaneous. Consisting of two boxes, this is the largest series in the collection. Howard's professional files include grants, presentations, promotions, etc. His work with various activist organizations include files for particular organizations as well as files documenting his role in protests, marches, and other events. Conference files include promotional literature, correspondence, and notes from a variety of professional and community group conferences. Howard's research subseries contains many hand-written notes on a number of subjects ranging from Shirley Q. Liquor to sodomy. Clippings consists of newspaper clippings and printouts collected on LGBTQI topics in various regions in the country. Teaching and syllabi include not only Howard's syllabi from undergraduate work, but also syllabi, teaching evaluations and correspondence from his own teaching career at institutions such as Duke University, DeKalb College, King's College London, and University of York.
The Writing Series is divided into two series: Writings by Howard and Writings by Others. Writings by Howard includes notes, correspondence, releases and reviews of Howard's published books, articles and other chapter publications. Writing by Others includes bound stage and screen plays, and unpublished manuscripts. The works were given to Howard by the authors.
The Oral History Series contains oral history notes from about twenty-five interviewees. Relatedly, the Audiovisual Materials Series consists of thirty-three audiocassettes containing oral history interviews for Howard's book, Men Like That.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Howard, John, 1962-
Duke University. Dept. of History
Queer theory
Sex -- Southern States
Gay men -- Southern States
Gays -- United States
Duke University -- Homosexuality
Contents of Collection
- Personal Papers, 1986-2011, (15 folders)
  The Personal Papers Series includes items such as gallery/art show pamphlets, Novid Parsi's immigration file, a playlist for the Band Defunkt, diplomas, GRE/GMAT reports, and miscellaneous undergraduate paper topics. The series is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Art shows, galleries, concerts, 1991-1995 (Box 1)
  - Atlanta Pride celebration, 1995 (Box 1)
  - The Band Defunkt, playlist, Washington, DC 1986 (Box 1)
  - GMAT, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - GRE, 1990 (Box 1)
  - John D. Howard, Sr., 1992-1997 (Box 1)
  - "Icons of the Gay Community," Getty Image Gallery, 2005 (Box 1)
  - McMillan, George, 1993-2011 (Box 1)
  - Nguyen, Brice, Paris, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous paper topics, undergraduate, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Parsi, Novid, immigration case, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Diplomas, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - Seen and Heard, Alabama, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Sligh, Charlie, undated (Box 1)
- Professional Papers, 1980-2013, (2 boxes)
  The Professional Papers Series is divided into eight subseries: professional, activist organizations, conferences, research, clippings, correspondence, teaching and miscellaneous. Each subseries is arranged in alphabetical order.
  Box 5 includes items restricted according to the University Archives regulations.
  - Professional, 1985-2009, (1 box)
    Materials include invitations to speak at universities, grants, presentations, guest lectures, documentaries, items pertaining to his tenure at The National Faculty, promotions, seminars, letters of recommendation, and the Historians' Amicus Brief, Supreme Court, Lawrence v. Texas.
    - American Museum in Britain, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Atlanta Gay and Lesbian Arts Festival, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Bachelor Farmers documentary, Kendrick, Idaho, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Berkeley-Bain, 2000 (Box 1)
    - British Museum, 2008 (Box 1)
    - Center for the History of Sexuality, undated (Box 1)
    - Center for Gay and Lesbian Studies, 1992-1995 (Box 1)
    - CLGH of AHA, undated (Box 1)
    - Delfina Studio Trust, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Driffield School, undated (Box 1)
    - Employment Non-Discrimination Act (ENDA), HRC, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - ESRC-Sexuality, York University and UCRYSJ, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Grants, 2000-2010 (Box 1)
    - Grants, Fulbright, 2000-2005 (Box 1)
    - Gulf States/Warner Collection firing, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Inter-Development Bank employment, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Inter-Development Bank evaluations, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Interdisciplinary Studies catalogue, Duke University, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Jesus College, Oxford University, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Job Clinic, 1988 (Box 1)
    - The Joneses, 2009 (Box 1)
    - The Joys and Limits of Gay Sex (chats), 2001 (Box 1)
    - King's College London Student Union, 2004 (Box 1)
    - King's College London/York, professional, 1998-2007 (Box 1)
    - Koessler benefaction, University of York, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Lawrence vs. Texas, Historians' Amicus Brief, 2003 (Box 1)
    - The National Faculty, forum/annual reports, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - The National Faculty, performance evaluations/indicators, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - The National Faculty, daily lists of activities, 1996 (Box 1)
    - The National Faculty, 1998 (Box 1)
    - "New Sexual Values," Reel Jems documentary, 2007 (Box 1)
    - "Politics of Dancing," correspondence, research, 1995-2001 (Box 1)
    - Promotions, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Publishers/publications, 1991-1995 (Box 1)
    - Queer Center seminar, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Letters of recommendation for J. Howard, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Resume, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - Shenshu University, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Southern Culture Collaborative Program, High Museum, 1996 (Box 1)
    - The Southern Historian, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Stonewall Leadership Programme, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Supervisees/dissertations, 1999-2002 (Box 1)
    - Swearer Center for Public Service, Brown University, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Tuscon, Arizona, lecture, undated (Box 1)
    - University of Reading donation, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Valentine Museum, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Warwick History Seminar, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Activist Organizations, 1990-2013, (22 folders)
    Organizations represented include Atlanta Lesbian and Gay History Thing, The Gay, Lesbian and Bisexual Alliance of the University of Alabama, Mary Renault Society, Queer Nation, amongst others. The subseries also consists of the activist events pertaining to the Cracker Barrel.
    - Atlanta Domestic Partnership, undated (Box 2)
    - Atlanta Lesbian and Gay History Thing, undated (Box 2)
    - Atlanta Lesbian and Gay Public Safety Task Force, 1992, (2 folders (Box 2)
    - Cheek, Jeff, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Cracker Barrel, 1993-2003 (Box 2)
    - Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Student Leaders meeting, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Gay campus organizations, 1990 and undated (Box 2)
    - GLAAD, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Gay, Lesbian, and Bisexual Alliance and the University of Alabama, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Lambda Update, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Chelsea/Bradley Manning, 2013 (Box 2)
    - March on Washington, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Mary Renault Society, 1997 (Box 2)
    - MS State University - Reflector, 1990 (Box 2)
    - National Coming Out Day, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Queer Nation, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - SAGA newsletter, 1992 (Box 2)
    - San Francisco AIDS Foundation, undated (Box 2)
    - Southern Oral History organization, 1993-1995 (Box 2)
    - Yorkshire Evening Press, 2001 (Box 2)
    - General activism (Box 2)
  - Conferences, 1991-2010, (11 folders) (Box 2)
    Conferences attended include the Queer History Conference, Queer Matters Conference, Sex Show Conference, the Southern Conference on Afro-American Studies, and several others. Files arranged alphabetically by conference title.
  - Research, 1980-2004, (9 folders) (Box 2)
    This subseries includes research on subjects such as sodomy, Shirley Q. Liquor, James Buchanon, and also includes photos from a Delta State Yearbook. Files arranged alphabetically.
  - Clippings, undated, (8 folders) (Box 2)
    Clippings concern LGBTQI issues in Alabama, Atlanta/Emory University, and Duke University. Also includes clippings on non-gay issues in the south.
  - Correspondence, 1996-2007, (10 folders) (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence with other authors, students, and fans. Files arranged alphabetically.
  - Teaching/syllabi, 1991-2008, (68 folders)
    Includes not only syllabi from Howard's graduate studies, but also syllabi, teaching evaluations and correspondence from Howard's tenure at King's College London, York University, Duke University and DeKalb among others.
    - DeKalb College, 1993-1994, (7 folders) (Box 3)
    - Teaching evaluations (Box 3)
    - American Studies courses, 1991-1992, (9 folders) (Box 3)
    - Duke History courses, (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - Emory graduate studies, (16 folders) (Box 3)
    - Queer studies syllabi, 1991-2000, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - King's College London courses, 2001-2009, (13 folders) (Box 3)
    - University of York courses, 1999-2001, (14 folders) (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous teaching files, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 2013 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    Items include a picture, some handwritten quotes and a written tribute to Ruby Etta Lee Koppelman.
  - University Archives Restricted Materials, (3 folders)
    Box 6 includes items restricted according to the University Archives policies.
    - Duke LGBT Center (Box 6)
    - Duke adjunct professorship offer (Box 6)
    - Email addresses/lists, 1998 (Box 6)
- Writings, 1950-2012
  - Writings by Howard, 1950-2012, (19 folders)
    Includes notes, correspondence and reviews of Howard's published work. Works include Carryin' on in the Lesbian and Gay South, The Bitterweed Path, and Men Like That: A Southern Queer History. Works are arranged in alphabetical order by title.
    - Bitterweed Path, 1950-1998, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Carryin' On in the Lesbian and Gay South anthology, 1993-1997, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - "An Emerging Voice," 1997 (Box 5)
    - Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Community Studies, 1996 (Box 5)
    - The Library, the Park, and the Pervert, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Monographs, contracts, and royalties, 1998-2011 (Box 5)
    - Men Like That, 1996-2001, (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - No Deed But Memory anthology, 1999 (Box 5)
    - OT Cabbage and Kings, 2012 (Box 5)
    - Oxford Student, 2006 (Box 5)
    - Same Language, with Ben Duncan, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Review of "Smearing the Queer," 2000 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous writings, 1992-1996 (Box 5)
  - Writings by Others, 1989-2012, (13 folders)
    Series includes bound stage and screen plays, and unpublished manuscripts--given by the authors to Howard. Authors include Patrick Cather, Ben Duncan, Novid Parsi, among others. Also included are two printed reports by organizations. Works are arranged in alphabetical order by author.
    - Araki, Gregg, The Living End, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Bailey, Brad, Womenfolks, c. 1995 (Box 3)
    - Blakely, Cynthia, Living Year-Round, 2005 (Box 4)
    - Cather, Patrick, She Really Was a Sick Woman, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Cather, Patrick, The Last Apollo Ball, 1995 and 1996, (2 versions) (Box 4)
    - Cather, Patrick, Where I Am Now, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Chapman, Dick, ed., Sydney Chapman Diaries: 1910 and After, 2012 (Box 4)
    - Duberman, Martin, Posing Naked, undated (Box 4)
    - Duncan, Ben, Late Starter, undated (Box 4)
    - Lee, Harper, Romance and High Adventure, 1993 (Box 4)
    - Stabler, Vastine, Al Dempart for Governor, undated (Box 4)
    - Louisiana Advisory Committee to the United States Commission on Civil Rights, The Administration of Justice for Homosexual Persons in New Orleans, September 1989 (Box 4)
    - North Carolina Coalition for Gay and Lesbian Equality, Homophobia and Human Rights in North Carolina, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Articles by Novid Parsi, undated (Box 4)
    - Raffl, Lea, and Elke Zobl, "Architectural Otherness: The Collision of Private and Public Space in the Case of Tearooms at Duke University," 1996 (Box 4)
    - Gay and Lesbian Studies, miscellaneous articles, undated (Box 4)
- Oral Histories, 1972-2010, (32 folders)
  Comprises oral history notes for Howard's research, including the work Men Like That, A Southern Queer History. The interviews were conducted by either John Howard or the Mississippi Oral History Program at The University of Southern Mississippi, abbreviated JH and MOHP respectively.
  - Barlow, Gary, 1993 (MOHP) (Box 5)
  - Barnes, Barbara, and Jenny Freedle, 1994 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Barnes, Thelma, 1996 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Clay, Henry, and Effie Clay, 1996 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Corley, Carl, 1999-2010 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Dent, Bill, 1996 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Doe, John, 1996 (MOHP) (Box 5)
  - Entrekin, Rod, 1996 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Fruitiger, Donald and Marvin Graham, 1993 (MOHP) (Box 5)
  - Grantham, Ken, 1996 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Griffis, Marcia, 1996 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Hammond, Jack, 1997 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Henry, Aaron, 1972 and undated (JH) (Box 5)
  - Higgs, Bill, 1998 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Hollingshead, Bennie, 1993 (MOHP) (Box 5)
  - Jones, Jheri, 1996 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Lever, John, 1994 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Lewis, Cathy, 1993 (MOHP) (Box 5)
  - Mauldin, Harry David, 1993 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Morey, Hunter, 1998 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Owen, Walter, 1996 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Reynolds, Edie, 1994 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Russell, Theodore, 1997 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Sakamoto, Hideo, 2000 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Sandifer, Eddie, 1996 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Schwartz, Jerome, 1993 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Schwartz, Perry, 1993 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Smith, Don, 1998 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Smith, Ms., 1993 (MOHP) (Box 5)
  - Wilds, Newt, and Bob Canon, 1997-2000 (JH) (Box 5)
  - MCC Interviews: Kathy Switzer, 1994 (JH) (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous interviews, 1994-1997 (JH) (Box 5)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1993-1998, (1 boxes)
  Series contains thirty-three audio-cassettes with oral history interviews for Men Like That, A Southern Queer History.
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - Barnes, Barbara, 1994 June 16 (Box 7)
    RL10076-CS-0001
  - Bender, James, 1994 Sept. 9 (Box 7)
    RL10076-CS-0002
  - Clay, Henry C. Jr., 1996 Jan. 13, (2 audio tapes) (Box 7)
    RL10076-CS-0003 and RL10076-CS-0004
  - Corley, Carl Vernon, 1997 July 29 (Box 7)
    RL10076-CS-0005
  - Dent, William, 1996 May 18 (Box 7)
    RL10076-CS-0006
  - Entreken, Rod L., 1996 Jan. 13 (Box 7)
    RL10076-CS-0007
  - Freedle, Jenny, 1994 June 16 (Box 7)
    RL10076-CS-0008
  - Grantham, Kenneth, 1996 May 19, (2 audio tapes) (Box 7)
    RL10076-CS-0009 and RL10076-CS-0010
  - Griffis, Marcia, 1996 June 21 (Box 7)
    RL10076-CS-0011
  - Hammond, Jack, 1996 May 18 and 1996 July 6, (3 audio tapes) (Box 7)
    RL10076-CS-0012, RL10076-CS-0013 and RL10076-CS-0014
  - Jones, Jheri, 1996 Jan. 14 (Box 7)
    RL10076-CS-0015
  - Lever, John, 1994 June 15, (2 audio tapes) (Box 7)
    RL10076-CS-0016 and RL10076-CS-0017
  - Mauldin, H. Donald, 1993 Sept. 4, (2 audio tapes) (Box 8)
    RL10076-CS-0018 and RL10076-CS-0019
  - Owen, Walter, 1996 July 6 (Box 8)
    RL10076-CS-0020
  - Paynther, Kevin (Brad Stone), 1994 Sept. 8 (Box 8)
    RL10076-CS-0021
  - Phillips, Thomas Hal, 1994 Nov. 25, 1995 July 18, 1995 Dec. 27, (4 audio tapes) (Box 8)
    RL10076-CS-0022, RL10076-CS-0023, RL10076-CS-0024 and RL10076-CS-0025
  - Reynolds, Edie, 1994 Sept. 19, (2 audio tapes) (Box 8)
    RL10076-CS-0026 and RL10076-CS-0027
  - Sandifer, Eddie, 1998 July 29 (Box 8)
    RL10076-CS-0028
  - Smith, Don, 1998 July 21 (Box 8)
    RL10076-CS-0029
  - Wild, Newt and Bob Canon, 1996 May 26, (2 audio tapes) (Box 8)
    RL10076-CS-0030 and RL10076-CS-0031
  - Ode to Billie Joe, 1994 Feb. 23, 1994 Mar. 2 (Box 8)
    RL10076-CS-0032
  - MCC Interviews: Kathy Switzer, 1994 Mar. 28 (Box 8)
    RL10076-CS-0033